{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "Article 359 of the Constitution authorizes the president of India to suspend the right to move any court for the enforcement of Fundamental Rights during :\n",
            "optionA": "  A National Emergency ",
            "optionB": "  A failure of constitutional machinery in States ",
            "optionC": "  A financial emergency ",
            "optionD": "  None of Above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhere a Proclamation of Emergency is in operation, the President may by order declare that the right to move any court for the enforcement of such of 1[the rights conferred by Part III (except articles 20 and 21)] as may be mentioned in the order and all proceedings pending in any court for the enforcement of the rights so mentioned shall remain suspended for the period during which the Proclamation is in force or for such shorter period as may be specified in the order. ",
            "keyString": "497244s2m40h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The correct chronological order of the formation of Haryana, Sikkim, Arunanchal Pradesh and Nagaland as full states of Indian Union is :",
            "optionA": "  Haryana-Sikkim-Arunachal Pardesh-Nagaland ",
            "optionB": "  Nagaland-Arunachal  Pradesh- Haryana-Sikkim ",
            "optionC": "  Nagaland-Haryana-Arunachal Pradesh-Sikkim ",
            "optionD": "  Nagaland-Haryana-Sikkim-Arunachal  Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNagaland on 1st December 1963. Haryana on 1st November 1966. Sikkim on 16th May 1975. Arunachal Pradesh on 20th Feb 1987. ",
            "keyString": "497274s2m40h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The speaker of the Lok Sabha can ask a member of the house to stop speaking and let another member speak. This phenomenon is known as :\n",
            "optionA": "  Crossing the floor ",
            "optionB": "  Yielding the floor ",
            "optionC": "  Point of Order ",
            "optionD": "  Calling Attention Motion ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:Yielding the floor. The speaker of the Lok sabha can ask a member of the house to stop speaking and let another member speak. Crossing the floor: Passing between the member addressing the House and the Chair which is considered breach of Parliamentary etiquette. Point of Order: A Member of Parliament may raise a point of order if he feels that the proceedings of' the House do not follow the normal rules. The presiding officer decides whether the point of order raised by the member should be allowed. Calling Attention Motion: With the prior permission of the Speaker, any member of the Parliament may call the attention of a Minister to a matter of urgent public importance. The Minister may make a brief statement about the matter or he may ask for time to make a statement later. ",
            "keyString": "497289s2m40h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which Constitutional Amendment Act was the number of Lok sabha seats increased from 525 to 545 ?\n\n",
            "optionA": "   The Twentieth Amendment Act, 1966. ",
            "optionB": "  The Forty-second Amendment Act, 1976.  ",
            "optionC": "  The Forty-fourth Amendment Act, 1978. ",
            "optionD": "  Thirty-first Constitutional  Amendment  Act, 1973. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t31st Constitutional Amendment Act, 1973 - By this amendment the seats of Lok Sabha was increased from 525 to 545 but reduced the representatior of UT's in Lok Sabha from 25 to 20. ",
            "keyString": "497301s2m40h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Backward Class commission was appointed in 1953 under the chairmanship of :\n\n\u00a0\n",
            "optionA": "  Deepak Katole ",
            "optionB": "  S.K.Kharventhan ",
            "optionC": "  Kaka  Kalelkar ",
            "optionD": "  Shakeel-uz-Zaman Ansari ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:Kaka Kalelkar Commission:The Backward Class Commission was appointed in 1953 with Kaka Kalelkar as the Chairman. The Commission was asked to determine the criteria to be adopted to provide concessions to \u201csocially and educationally backward classes\u201d besides the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes; the Commission was also asked to prepare a list of such classes. ",
            "keyString": "497312s2m40h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "\"Milind Panho\" explaining the Buddhist doctrines in the form of a dialogue between Milind and his teacher Nagsena (the great Buddhist philosopher ) is in :\n",
            "optionA": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionB": "  Pali Language ",
            "optionC": "  Hindi ",
            "optionD": "  Santhali ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:Pali Language. ",
            "keyString": "766231s24m54h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahabhasya - an outstanding work in the fields of grammar - is a composition by:",
            "optionA": "  Ashwins ",
            "optionB": "  Ghosha ",
            "optionC": "  Kakshivat ",
            "optionD": "  Patanjali ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Mahabhasya - an outstanding work in the fields of grammar - is a composition by Patanjali.",
            "keyString": "766279s24m54h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1724 the state of Hyderabad was founded by : ",
            "optionA": "  Nizam-ul-Mulk Asaf-Jah ",
            "optionB": "  Azim Jah Bahadur ",
            "optionC": "  Osman Ali Khan ",
            "optionD": "  Qamaruddin Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHyderabad State was founded by Mir Qamar-ud-din Khan who was the governor of Deccan under the Mughals from 1713 to 1721. In 1724, he resumed rule under the title of Asaf Jah (granted by Mughal Emperor Muhammad Shah).",
            "keyString": "766293s24m54h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Annie Besant arrived in India in:",
            "optionA": "  1878 ",
            "optionB": "  1885 ",
            "optionC": "  1893 ",
            "optionD": "  1900 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDr Besant arrived in India in 1893 to spread the message of the Theosophical Society, a religious movement based on the principles of karma and reincarnation. A champion of social and political reform, she soon became involved in India's freedom struggle.",
            "keyString": "766307s24m54h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi laid down four preconditions for a Satyagrahi  (Passive Resistor) to fulfill - namely :",
            "optionA": "  Observe perfect Chastity, Adopt Poverty, Follow truth and Cultivated Fearlessness. ",
            "optionB": "  Observe perfect Chastity, Gain Money, Follow truth and Cultivated Fearlessness. ",
            "optionC": "  Observe perfect Chastity, Adopt Poverty, Follow truth and Cultivated Power. ",
            "optionD": "  Observe perfect Chastity, Gain Money, Follow truth and Cultivated Power. ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tObserve perfect Chastity, adopt Poverty, Follow truth and Cultivated Fearlessness.",
            "keyString": "766319s24m54h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Between 1749-1754, an important war fought between the forces of the British and the French is known as : ",
            "optionA": "  Third battale of panipat ",
            "optionB": "  The first Carnatic War ",
            "optionC": "  The second Carnatic War ",
            "optionD": "  Battle of Baxur ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBetween 1749-1754, an important war fought between the forces of the British and the French is known as the second Carnatic War.",
            "keyString": "800346s24m54h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Dutch East India Company was formed by merging several small companies of Holland in :",
            "optionA": "  The year 1702 ",
            "optionB": "  The year 1602 ",
            "optionC": "  The year 1802 ",
            "optionD": "  The year 1834 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Dutch East India Company was formed by merging several small companies of Holland in the year 1602.",
            "keyString": "800376s24m54h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Harappa Civilization was discovered in 1920-21 by the excavations by :",
            "optionA": "  R.",
            "optionB": " Banerjee and by ",
            "optionC": "R. Sahni ",
            "optionD": "  Mortimer Wheeler ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tR.D. Banerjee at Mohenjodaro and by D.R. Sahni at Harappa",
            "keyString": "800391s24m54h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most distinguishing feature of various  Chalcolithic Cultures in ancient period is their :",
            "optionA": "  Black Polished Ware  ",
            "optionB": "  Seal  ",
            "optionC": "  Painted Grey Ware ",
            "optionD": "  Painted Pottery ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t The most distinguishing feature of various Chalcolithic Cultures in ancient period is their painted pottery.",
            "keyString": "800404s24m54h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mughal emperor Akbar divided his empire into :",
            "optionA": "  Eight Provinces (Subas) ",
            "optionB": "  Five Provinces (Subas) ",
            "optionC": "  Twelve Provinces (Subas) ",
            "optionD": "  Ten Provinces (Subas) ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInitially, after the administrative reforms of Akbar, the Mughal empire was divided into 12 subahs : Kabul, Lahore, Multan, Delhi, Agra, Avadh, Illahabad, Bihar, Bangalah, Malwa, Ajmer and Gujarat. ",
            "keyString": "800416s24m54h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}